September 21st, 2010 - TrueZIP 6.8 has been released

I am pleased to announce the release of TrueZIP 6.8. This is a maintenance release - it fixes classloading for OSGI environments, updates the Javadoc and fixes some issues with the unit tests for Swing GUI classes.

Last, but not least, Maven is now used for the build and release process. The Maven Coordinates are de.schlichtherle:truezip:jar:6.8. You should soon see the artifacts appear in Maven Central.

If and only if you are using TrueZIP to access TAR files or derivative archive file types, then you need to upgrade the run time dependency ant.jar to Ant 1.8.1.

Upgrading is recommended for all users.

For more details, please refer to the Release Notes.

July 16th, 2010 - TrueZIP 6.7 has been released

I am pleased to announce the final release of TrueZIP 6.7. This is a feature and maintenance release. The primary objective of this release is to add transparent ZIP64 support and increase the interoperability of ZIP files with third party utilities such as Windows Explorer, WinZip, 7-Zip and others. Upgrading is recommended for all users because there have been a few minor bug fixes since the Release Candidate 1.

For more details, please refer to the Release Notes.

November 3rd, 2009 - TrueZIP 6.7 Release Candidate 1 has been released

I am pleased to announce Release Candidate 1 for TrueZIP 6.7. After two years since the release of version 6.6, this is a feature and maintenance release. The primary objective of this release is to increase the interoperability of ZIP files with third party utilities such as Windows Explorer, WinZip, 7-Zip and others. Upgrading is recommended for all users.

Long awaited, this is the first release which supports ZIP64 extensions. As far as I know TrueZIP 6.7 is the first open source Java implementation of ZIP64 extensions at all. This enables client applications to read and write ZIP archive files of more than 4GB size. Handling ZIP64 extensions is fully transparent for client applications, so there are no public API changes involved. By default, ZIP64 extensions are written to a ZIP file if and only if they are required so that maximum interoperability with third party tools is retained.

Furthermore, a new date/time conversion algorithm has been introduced for plain ZIP files. This enhances accuracy of time stamps when exchanging ZIP files with third party tools like Windows Explorer, WinZip, 7-Zip and others. It also eliminates issues with the daylight saving time if the schedule has changed between the last modification time of an archive entry and the current system time. Of course, the date/time conversion algorithm for the JAR file family hasn't changed.

Client applications using the high level API in the package de.schlichtherle.io automatically benefit from this enhancement. Client applications using the low level API in the package de.schlichtherle.util.zip need to subclass the class ZipEntry and override the method getDateTimeConverter().

I sincerely thank Roedy Green from Canadian Mind Products for prodding me at the issue with date/time conversion in plain ZIP files! I also sincerely thank everybody who has helped me to develop this version by donating to this project: Your donation is really appreciated - thank you very much!

For more details, please refer to the Release Notes.

April 3rd, 2007 - TrueZIP 6.6 has been released

This is a maintenance release. For more details, please refer to the Release Notes. Upgrading is optional for all users.

February 27th, 2007 - TrueZIP 6.5.4 has been released

This is a feature and update release. TrueZIP 6.5.4 reads/writes OpenDocument Format (ODF) files, enhances creation and ordering of entries in archive files, enhances concurrency, enhances the Javadoc, fixes all known bugs and has been fortified with more unit tests and FindBugs. For more details, please refer to the Release Notes. Upgrading is recommended for all users.

December 21st, 2006 - TrueZIP 6.4 has been released

It's only a minor release number increase, but it's a major improvement: TrueZIP 6.4 fixes all known bugs, significantly improves performance in many sectors and comes with a rigorously updated Javadoc for the package de.schlichtherle.io.

TrueZIP 6.4 is now a first class citizen on Linux, too: On this platform, previous releases where painfully slow when using RAES encrypted ZIP files and showed some bugs when using GUI classes like JFileChooser or the Swing based key manager implementation.

A new feature has been added, too: When prompting for keys for RAES encrypted ZIP files on a JVM which is running in headless mode, TrueZIP 6.4 now prompts the user on the console. This feature requires JSE 6 as the runtime environment.

Backwards compatibility is retained: TrueZIP 6.4 runs on any J2SE 1.4.2 compliant JRE. Recompilation of existing applications is not required.

For more information, please refer to the Release Notes. Upgrading is highly recommended for all users.

Oct. 10th, 2006 - TrueZIP 6.3.1 has been released

This is a minor bug fix release. A single typing error has been fixed which unfortunately rendered File.update/umount(File, ...) completely useless. A unit test has been added for File.update(File) in particular to test this in future. My apologies to all affected users - please upgrade.

Oct. 6th, 2006 - TrueZIP 6.3 has been released

This is a minor feature release which adds some new update to make it easier to update/unmount archive files safely in multithreaded environments. A few minor bugs have been fixed, too. For more information, please refer to the Release Notes.

Sep. 7th, 2006 - TrueZIP 6.2.1 has been released

This is a maintenance release.

Enhanced: Exception messages have been revised in various packages in order to provide more meaningful information, helping developers to understand the root cause.
Fixed: The methods en/decrypt in the class de.schlichtherle.io.RaesFileUtils looked up the key using the normal path name instead of the canonical path name.

The API has been kept fully backward compatible, so that client applications do not need to get recompiled.

Aug. 7th, 2006 - TrueZIP 6.2 and 5.1.8 have been released

For TrueZIP 6.2, this is a maintenance and feature release. The primary focus has been to optimize multithreading performance, fix minor bugs and enhance the Javadoc. Updating is recommended for multithreaded environments such as application servers.

The new feature in TrueZIP 6.2 is a really cool class which provides auto completion of file names in an attached JComboBox. This provides users with a very convenient way to browse their file system. Of course, this includes support for browsing archive files. Subclassing JComboBox.or using a particular ComboBoxModel is not required. Please refer to the Javadoc for the class de.schlichtherle.io.swing.FileComboBoxBrowser for more information.

For TrueZIP 5.1.8, this is a bug fix release. It also marks the End Of Life for TrueZIP 5 as TrueZIP 7 has entered the design phase and maintenance of then three releases takes too much resources.

For more information about the new releases, please refer to the...

Release Notes for TrueZIP 6.2
Release Notes for TrueZIP 5.1.8

Jul. 10th, 2006 - TrueZIP 6.1 and 5.1.7 have been released

Another double release for TrueZIP. This is a bug fix and minor feature release. The primary focus has been to fix multithreading issues and enhance the Javadoc. The new feature is the extension of the ZIP archive driver family with CRC-32 checked versions for optional usage. Updating is considered critical for multithreaded environments such as application servers.

For more information about the new releases, please refer to the...

Release Notes for TrueZIP 6.1
Release Notes for TrueZIP 5.1.7

Apr. 5th, 2006 - TrueZIP 6.0 and 5.1.6 have been released

The final version for TrueZIP 6.0 has been released. This is a major update with some exciting new features:

A plug-in "driver" architecture for virtually any archive type. This allows third parties to provide support for arbitrary archive types.
Out-of-the-box support for TAR, TAR.GZ and TAR.BZ2 archives using the new "plug-in driver" architecture. As usual with TrueZIP, this allows an application to address any entry in a TAR archive by specifying the archive as part of the path name, such as e.g. "src.tar.gz/inner.zip/readme.html".
Some minor bugs have been fixed, too. The majority of these bugs were found in the Swing components PromptingKeyManager (refactored from the former PasswdManager), JFileChooser and JFileTree.

In fact, this is a double release: For maintenance reasons, TrueZIP 5.1.6 is also available now. This version should contain all the bug fixes which were introduced with TrueZIP 6.0, too.

New applications should always use TrueZIP 6 for its enhanced architecture and performance. In case you used TrueZIP 5.X or a Release Candidate of TrueZIP 6, you need to recompile your client application. For more information about this release and migration from former releases, please refer to the Release Notes for TrueZIP 6.0.

Mar. 13th, 2006 - TrueZIP 6.0 Release Candidate 1 is available. This is a major update release with support for TAR, TAR.GZ and TAR.BZ2 archives.

TrueZIP 6.0 provides some exciting new features:

A plug-in "driver" architecture for virtually any archive type. This allows third parties to provide support for arbitrary archive types, such as RAR or ARJ (volunteers wanted!).
Out-of-the-box support for TAR, TAR.GZ and TAR.BZ2 archive using the new "plug-in driver" architecture. As usual with TrueZIP, this allows an application to address any entry in a TAR archive by specifying the archive as part of the path name, such as e.g. "src.tar.gz/inner.zip/readme.html".
ZIP64 is going to be added soon. However, it is still not decided yet whether this will be available with the official TrueZIP 6.0 release or deferred to the release of TrueZIP 6.1 instead. I prefer to have short release cycles, so it is likely that you may see this in TrueZIP 6.1.

Mar. 6th, 2006 - TrueZIP 6.0 is in development. This will be a major update release with support for TAR archives and much more.

TrueZIP 6 will provide some exciting new features:

A plug-in "driver" architecture for any archive type. This allows third parties to provide support for virtually any archive type, such as RAR or ARJ.
Out-of-the-box support for TAR, TAR.GZ and TAR.BZ2 archive using the new archive "driver" architecture. As usual with TrueZIP, this will allow an application to address any entry in a TAR archive by specifying the archive as part of the path name, such as e.g. "src.tar.gz/readme.html".
Out-of-the-box support for ZIP64 archives in order to break the 4GB limitation of the current ZIP32 implementation. However, please note that in order to provide a short release cycle, this may be deferred to the release of TrueZIP 6.1 instead of TrueZIP 6.0.
And some other goodies as well, but I don't want to promise too much yet...

The current status is that the TAR support is already implemented and working (i.e. passes all JUnit tests). The archive driver interface has yet to be refactored again in order to remove all of the ZIP32 specific legacy. A beta release is planned for next week. This release will be stable (i.e. passes all JUnit tests), but may be subject to some more refactorings.

Besides of all the good news, there is also some not-so-good-news: In order to abstract TrueZIP from ZIP32, some public API classes and interfaces had to be refactored. So if your application is not just using basic file I/O, it is likely that you will have to refactor some of your code. For this reason, TrueZIP 5.1 is and will be continued to be maintained, i.e. all bugs will be fixed and minor enhancements will be added (but no big features).

So application developers have the choice to stay with TrueZIP 5.1.X and be on the safe side in terms of bug fixes and regular maintenance or switching to TrueZIP 6 to take advantage of the support for all the new archive types.

Mar. 6th, 2006 - TrueZIP 5.1.5 has been released. This is a minor bug fix and maintenance release.

Fixed: When using ZIP files created by other tools which contained dot or dot-dot directories in their entry name (e.g. "./file.txt"), TrueZIP wasn't able to address these entries properly.
Fixed: The constructors of the File class didn't ignore empty directory members (e.g. "dir//file.txt") in path names.
Fixed: The last modification time attribute was copied when using a normal File.copy*(*) method instead of File.archiveCopy*(*).
Enhanced: File constructor performance. This cuts down the runtime of some JUnit tests by a third!

Feb. 24th, 2006 - TrueZIP 5.1.2 has been released. This is a feature enhancement and bug fix release.

Following is a high level overview of the changes/add-ons (in order of priority):

New: New classes have been added to support JTree based traversal of directory trees, including support for any ZIP compatible file type of course. Please check out the classes JFileTree, FileTreeModel and FileTreeCellRenderer in the packages de.schlichtherle.io.swing and de.schlichtherle.io.swing.tree. The JFileTree class is a complete file system browser, providing GUI aware file operations like createNewFile, mkdir, copyTo, renameTo, delete, deleteAll, etc. It uses system icons for all nodes, provides options which control how to deal with suffixes, uses filters and allows you to rename files and directories by editing their node. A tutorial for this class should be added later.
New: TrueZIP is now able to read and update Self Extracting Archives, such as produced by WinZIP or JSmooth for example. However, please be aware that the SFX code of these applications does not tolerate updating their ZIP file contents. So once updated, you cannot use the SFX code anymore, but you can still use the regular tools (e.g. WinZIP or infoZIP) to access the updated ZIP file contents. This restriction is imposed by the SFX code and cannot be resolved by TrueZIP.
New: When using characters in file names which have no representation in the character set encoding of the target ZIP compatible file, then the TrueZIP API will fail gracefully with an IOException or a boolean return value of false (depending on the method's way to indicate an error condition). This is to protect applications from creating ZIP entries which cannot get encoded and decoded again correctly. An example is the Euro sign which does not have a representation in the IBM437 character set used by ordinary ZIP files.
Enhanced: The PasswdManager class has been refactored to allow easy programmatic setting of RaesParameters for a particular file without the need to implement a custom ZipDetector.
Enhanced: The SwingPasswdManager class now implements focus management for more convenient password editing.
Enhanced: The performance has been further enhanced by reimplementing the constructors of the File class and the low level ZipFile class.
Fixed: Some minor bugs have been fixed, none of which caused ZIP file corruptions.
Retained: Binary compatibility of truezip.jar.
Updated: Project management files are now upgraded to NetBeans 5 and have been enhanced to support some versioning information in the source files.

Jan. 24th, 2006 - TrueZIP 5.0.1 has been released. This is a minor bug fix release.

A regression bug has been fixed which caused the nzip utility main class to identify ZIP and RAES encrypted ZIP files only instead of all known ZIP compatible file types (i.e. EAR, JAR, WAR, ZIP and RAES encrypted ZIP files).

Jan. 20th, 2006 - TrueZIP 5.0 has been released. This is a major update providing significant performance increases by using asynchronous I/O, various new features, reduced memory footprint, enhanced internal exception handling and an extensible architecture to support binary backwards compatibility for future releases. All users are recommended to upgrade.

Please note that you must recompile your applications if you are using older versions of TrueZIP. This is primarily because of the refactorings in the File and ZipDetector classes. Regular applications should not have to change a single of code, however. Because TrueZIP's public API is now completely relying on Dependency Injection, Factory and Decorator patterns, this is hopefully the last update requiring public API refactorings and hence the last increase of the major version number for a while.

TrueZIP is used by commercial applications and so its primary objectives have always been stability and performance. Therefore, TrueZIP 5.0 has been tested with extended, comprehensive JUnit tests on the Windows, Linux and Mac OS X platform with a combination of JDK 1.4.2_10 and JDK 1.5.0_06 and numerous manual tests in a special test parcours (located in the false positive directory "1.zip") and with lots of ZIP files created by external tools, such as WinZIP, infoZIP and JSmooth.

Following is a high level overview of the changes/add-ons (in order of priority):

Enhanced: All cat and copy methods in the File class now use asynchronous IO similar to the transfer(...) method of the java.nio.Channel class. Various tests have shown that this cuts down the gross execution time for copying a file within the same folder by about 33%! Depending on the system configuration and source and target file location and size, your results may be even better! Because this is all based on the method File.cat(InputStream, OutputStream), you can use this feature for any kind of input or output stream in your applications!
New/Enhanced: The SwingPasswdManager class, which is used by default to manage encryption keys for RAES encrypted ZIP files, now also supports key file based encryption in addition to only password based encryption. All dialogs have been improved to enhance their overall usability.
Changed: The ZipDetector interface has been completely refactored to a factory pattern in order to support dependency injection for all required resources in the de.schlichtherle.io package (such as ZipFile and ZipOutputStream instances). Its member constant default implementations have been retained and extended however, so that regular applications should not be affected by this change unless they implement this interface.
New: The copyAll methods of the File class have new members which allow you to provide different ZipDetector instances for the source and destination directory tree. This allows you to do fancy stuff like changing the character set encoding of ZIP file entry names or unzipping a complete directory tree with recursively enclosed ZIP compatible files on the fly with a single API call. Please refer to the
Fixed: One major bug: If a ZIP compatible file created by an external application (such as WinZIP) contained any STORED instead of just DEFLATED entries (see PKWARE's ZIP File Format Specification ), updating its content caused the resulting ZIP compatible file to be corrupted.
Fixed: Various minor bugs, most of them about proper exception handling. TrueZIP's internal exception handling strategy is now pretty elaborate and should cause TrueZIP to fail gracefully in any case.

Dec. 19th, 2005 - TrueZIP 4.0 has been released. This is a major update. All users are recommended to upgrade.

In order of priority:

Enhanced: TrueZIP now correctly recognizes and handles all kinds of false positive ZIP compatible files. A false positive ZIP compatible file is a file or directory or a file or directory entry in an enclosing ZIP compatible file which looks like a ZIP compatible file by its path name (e.g. "archive.zip" or "outer.zip/inner.zip/secret.tzp"), but actually is a plain file or directory or an RAES encrypted ZIP file which's password could not be successfully requested from the user. The previous version only recognized and handled false positives which were actually plain files in the file system. Please note that TrueZIP does not (and never did and presumably never will) check the existence or integrity of the manifest in a JAR, EAR or WAR.
Enhanced/fixed: TrueZIP now provides its own implementation of the standard ZIP character set IBM437 (a.k.a. CP437, the original IBM PC character set for the United States and others). Previous versions silently reverted to UTF-8 (this is what Sun's java.util.zip package erratically uses) if CP437 is not installed in the JRE. However, at least on the Windows platform, CP437 is only installed if the user/administrator chose to install the international character sets in $java.home/lib/charsets.jar, which is more or less unlikely.
Fixed: Primarily a lot of bugs in the exception handling code (see above), but most notably the methods File.renameTo() and File.archiveCopyAll*() now treat directory timestamps correctly and refuse to rename/copy into themselves.
New/changed: The PasswdManager class, which is used to prompt users for passwords for RAES encrypted ZIP files, has been refactored to the package de.schlichtherle.crypto.io and heavily redesigned: For end users, the new version supports cancellation of password prompts for new encrypted ZIP files and automatically highlights file paths when they change. For application developers, a mechanism has been added to provide a custom password manager in case they don't want to use the default Swing based implementation. For more information, please refer to the PasswdManager class JavaDoc.
New: Some new methods have been added to the File class for convenience. Please check out the File class Javadoc.
New: New utility methods and main classes have been added to provide encryption and decryption of ordinary files into and from the RAES format. Please check out the source of the new main classes encrypt, decrypt and the JavaDoc for the utility class de.schlichtherle.io.RaesFileUtils.
Enhanced: For large ZIP compatible files (e.g. 2 GB) with thousands of entries (e.g. 24k) there is now a huge performance increase to mount the ZIP file system and update the target ZIP file.
New/changed: The ReadOnlyFile interface, which is part of the low level API and is used to read the ZIP file structure from plain or RAES encrypted files, and its companion implementation classes have been refactored to their own package de.schlichtherle.io.rof. New implementation classes which use NIO channels and memory mapped files are provided, too. Please note that these classes are not used within TrueZIP because of some painful bugs in the J2SE API on certain platforms (e.g. Windows and Linux). Please use where appropriate only.
Enhanced: The logging of the ZipController class has been enhanced. Please refer to the configuration file logging.properties for more information.

Please note that you should recompile your applications if you are using older versions of TrueZIP, unless you are only using (i.e. not implementing or subclassing interfaces or classes in) the High-Level-API, which consists of all classes in the package de.schlichtherle.io and the class de.schlichtherle.io.swing.FileSystemView. This is because the low level API has been heavily refactored and some of these changes emanate into the High-Level-API in order to support the new password manager for RAES encrypted ZIP files.

Dec. 5th, 2005 - TrueZIP 3.3 has been released. This is primarily a bug fix release. All users are recommended to upgrade.

The JFileChooser and FileSystemView classes in the package de.schlichtherle.io.swing have been fixed so that they work (almost) correctly now. Please note that there are still some minor issues left which unfortunately cannot get fixed because they are caused by the completely broken design and implementation of the JFileChooser, FileSystemView and companion classes in the genuine Java API (caused by scattered responsibilities for file properties and the implementation's heavy dependency on the API private ShellFolder class). However, I'm pretty confident that most users should hardly be able to tell a difference now.
TrueZIP's error handling has been further enhanced so that it now fails more gracefully on some odd (and unlikely) events in the native file system.
Support for Apple's Java 1.5 Release 1 on Mac OS X has been enhanced. Many, many thanks to Dr. Simon White from Catalysoft, Cambridge, UK for spending many hours to tackle down this issue.
A multithreading issue has been fixed which may have caused NullPointerException(s) somewhere deep in the Java regex API.
Last but not least, TrueZIP now provides basic support for Java's logging API in its package private class ZipController. If you ever wondered what happens under the hood of TrueZIP and when the update() or umount() method of the class File is automatically called, it is recommended to consult the file logging.properties in the source code distribution and edit it in order to log important events within TrueZIP.

Oct. 22nd, 2005 - TrueZIP 3.2 has been released. This is a maintenance release. All users are recommended to upgrade.

A bug in the conversion from DOS time (used in ZIP files) to Java/Unix time has been fixed.
The password dialogs now emit a beep before showing and properly display on JDK 5.
The performance of direct copying from a ZIP file entry to another ZIP file entry (maybe in the same ZIP file) has been slightly enhanced.
The class de.schlichtherle.io.swing.DefaultRaesZipDetector has been refactored to de.schlichtherle.io.DefaultRaesZipDetector.

Oct. 22nd, 2005 - TrueZIP 3.1 has been released. This version provides transparent access to RAES encrypted ZIP files, fixes some bugs and offers performance and memory optimizations. All users are recommended to upgrade.

Encryption

TrueZIP has been extended to provide transparent access to regular ZIP files which have been encrypted according to the Random Access Encryption Specification (RAES).

RAES has been developed because there is a significant need to encrypt ZIP files. However, existing de-facto standards are either patent bombed, such as PKWARE's AES encryption feature, or known to be more or less vulnerable as the article "Attacking and Repairing the WinZip Encryption Scheme" from Tadayoshi Kohno about WinZIP's proprietary AES encryption feature documents. Hence the need for a new format. However, this time the format (RAES) is designed to provide maximum security and flexibility as an extensible open source specification with an open source reference implementation as part of TrueZIP.

RAES is a file wrapping format that has been designed to provide secure, random access to arbitrary encrypted file contents - encrypting ZIP files is just one its applications. RAES features encryption according to the Advanced Encryption Standard (AES) with variable key sizes of 128, 192 and 256 bits. In order to provide maximum security, RAES encrypts the entire ZIP file (the content) and operates AES in Counter Mode (CTR), whereby its parameters are derived from a password according to the Public Key Cryptography Standard # 12 (PKCS #12). For parameter derivation, Message Authentication (MAC) and Pseudo Random Number Generation (PRNG), RAES uses the the Secure Hash Algorithm with 256 bit output (SHA-256). RAES is an extensible format - the next version is intended to provide certificate based encryption and authentication according to PKCS #12.

For more information about RAES, please refer to the class RandomAccessEncryptionSpecification in the package de.schlichtherle.crypto.io. If you would like to use an easy interface for reading and writing RAES files yourself, please check the RAES reference implementation classes RaesReadOnlyFile and RaesOutputStream in the same package.

Please note that some refactorings were necessary to introduce RAES encryption (most notably in the ZipDetector class) and consequently, all code marked as deprecated in previous versions has been removed. However, most applications should not be affected by this.

Bugs fixed

The bugs fixed for version 3.0 include, but are not limited to:

The interpretation of dot directories ("." and "..") is now correct.
TrueZIP is now aware of some specifics of the file system and J2SE behavior on Mac OS X. In particular, file name comparison is now working correctly.
Previous versions could deadlock or behave erratically when used in multithreading applications.
JFileChooser caused a NullPointerException if going up one directory on the Windows Desktop.
Writability tests have been fixed not to alter the last modification time if a file is already opened on Windows.
Various other minor fixes.

Bugs fixed for version 3.1:

A bug in the update strategy could have caused some directory time stamps to be incorrect if an application is accessing corrupted ZIP files.
The password manager now always resets the password display if prompting for new passwords.

A special thanks to Dr. Simon White for helping me to identify some of the bugs.

Optimizations

The performance and memory optimizations include, but are not limited to:

A new File.update() strategy offers enhanced performance by reducing I/O.
The memory footprint of the class ZipEntry has been slightly reduced. This may be important if you use ZIP files with thousands of entries.

Miscellaneous

A lot of new unit tests have been added in order to further harness the library and reduce the likeliness of bugs.

As usual, some work on the Javadoc has been spent to enhance it.